<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "docbookx.dtd">

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>FreeVikings Developer's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jakub</firstname> 
      <surname>Pavlik</surname>
      <email>severus@post.cz</email>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: INTRODUCTION.
       Who is this book for, what is it's aim, ... 
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      In January 2005 I wrote the first version of freeVikings, and, very
      proud of my first game (it was funless, boring, often crashing),
      published it on the Internet. A lot has changed since January 2005.
      I'm not so proud of my first game. And, I think, it's never more funless.
    </para>
    <para>
      FreeVikings now have several fancy features you expect a good game 
      to have. It's usually stable, 
      good-looking<footnote><para>This is a joke.
      Actually, freeVikings are still awful. I'm not able to do anything
      with this.</para></footnote> and extendable.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the developers make their application scriptable, they don't usually
      do it for themselves but for the users. Or they say they are doing it
      for users (everybody knows that the software developers only do things 
      for fun). FreeVikings are scriptable. 
      It means...<footnote><para>
      Yes, you're right. Actually it means I was playing with Ruby.
      But forget it, will you?</para></footnote>
      It means I want to give you the possibility
      of extending freeVikings with your own levels. You can catch
      Erik, Baleog and Olaf into your own traps. It seems good, doesn't it?
    </para>
    <para>
      So if you like freeVikings, have just a small amount of time for playing
      around a bit, ... Go on reading and make the best freeVikings level
      ever seen.
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FIRST MAP
       How to create your own map, how to make it running (tell freeVikings
       where to find it) 
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>First map</title>

    <para>
      This chapter will guide you through the first steps of the freeVikings
      level developer. You will start with clean hands and end with a ready
      to use map.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Requirements</title>
      <para>
	What do you need? At least you need a computer 
	with a running<footnote><para>At first I wrote "well running".
	Then I looked at the text I had just written. FreeVikings do never run
	well... And I retyped the sentence quickly.</para></footnote>
	freeVikings installation and some plain text editor.
	If I could recommend you some, I would tell you to choose 
	<application>GNU Emacs</application> (because I like this great beast),
	but any editor with XML syntax highlighting is good enough for our 
	purpose and you can, if you are some kind of fanatic, use
	<application>ed</application> od <application>NotePad</application>.
      </para>
      <sidebar>
	<title>Text-editing fanatism</title>
	<para>
	  Just a word on text-editing fanatism. I think you know some 
	  of the strange W!ndows users who say "NotePad forever!" and
	  "Anyone who doesn't write web pages in NotePad isn't a programmer".
	  What do they find so good on an editor which tries to save every
	  file with suffix .txt unless you click two times more than you want?
	</para>
	<para>
	  On they other hand I have heard about some old Un!x hackers who
	  hesitate to use any other text editor than ancient
	  <application>ed</application>. I don't understand them either but 
	  I think they feel some kind of nostalgy using the pure line-editing
	  stuff.
	</para>
      </sidebar>
      <para>
	Another good thig to install on your computer is 
	<application>Tiled</application>, a Java-written tile map editor.
	It allows you to develop maps quickly (and gives you more time for
	a much more interesting activity - scripting :o) ).
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="tiled.png"/>
      <para>
	<application>Tiled</application> produces simple but full-featured
	human-readable map files in XML format. Maybe you know (but I don't 
	think so) freeVikings have a native map format which is also subset
	of XML language (I like XML very much since I've first learned 
	about it). Support for <application>Tiled</application> maps was added
	experimentally in release 0.5 because I think possibility of creating
	maps in visual way will encourage people to create and share
	new levels.
      </para>
      <para>
	Just one more application. Some graphic editor for creating all kinds
	of graphics. I personally use <application>GIMP</application>.
	It has a lot of interesting features, is scriptable (do you know 
	Scheme? Don't you? It's fun!) and free (it means poor people
	don't have to download it from warez servers and you can download and
	read the whole source code if you want).
	You will need some graphic editor to make your own tilesets
	(those distributed with freeVikings aren't still any good) and maybe
	your own creatures to make the new levels more interesting.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FREEVIKINGS BASICS
       Basic concepts of the game world.
       What is the Location, StaticObjects, ActiveObjects, Sprites, Items,
       what are they good for.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: SCRIPTING
       Writing location scripts with all the fancy stuff.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: COOL STUFF
       About themes, passwords, level suites.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: HOW TO CONTRIBUTE
       How to give your masterpiece to the free world.
       ==================================================================== -->
</book>
