<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY part_levelcreationtutorial SYSTEM "leveltutorial.xml">
<!ENTITY part_graphicstandards SYSTEM "graphicstandards.xml">
]>

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>FreeVikings Developer's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jakub</firstname> 
      <surname>Pavlik</surname>
      <email>severus@post.cz</email>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      In January 2005 I wrote the first version of freeVikings, and, very
      proud of my first game (it was funless, boring, often crashing),
      published it on the Internet. A lot has changed since January 2005.
      I'm not so proud of my first game. And, I think, it's never more funless.
    </para>
    <para>
      FreeVikings now have several fancy features you expect a good game 
      to have. It's usually stable, 
      good-looking<footnote><para>This is a joke.
      Actually, freeVikings are still awful. I'm not able to do anything
      with this. And they often crash.</para></footnote> and extendable.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the developers make their application scriptable, they don't usually
      do it for themselves but for the users. Or they say they are doing it
      for users (everybody knows that the software developers only do things 
      for fun). FreeVikings are scriptable. 
      It means...<footnote><para>
      Yes, you're right. Actually it means I was playing with Ruby.
      But forget it, will you?</para></footnote>
      It means I want to give you the possibility
      of extending freeVikings with your own levels. You can catch
      Erik, Baleog and Olaf into your own traps. It seems good, doesn't it?
    </para>
    <para>
      So if you like freeVikings, have just a small amount of time for playing
      around a bit, ... Go on reading and make the best freeVikings level
      ever seen. Or maybe you aren't familiar with programming Ruby and
      don't want to crate new levels, but you can paint better images
      than me (nearly everyone can!) and want to make vikings, their
      enemies or some level nicer - yeah! Welcome! We need you!
    </para>
    <para>
      This development guide is being written in the time of creation of
      freeVikings v. 0.7. Some of the interfaces described below can be changed
      in the future. Please, inform me if you find out that the examples 
      from this guide don't work or some interfaces don't behave as it is 
      described here.
    </para>
    <para>
      Everything in this guide is explained in the environment of unix-like
      operating system such as Linux. I would like to apologize to all the
      poor non-unix-systems-users.
    </para>
  </preface>

  <!-- Parts -->
  &part_levelcreationtutorial;
  &part_graphicstandards;
</book>
