<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "docbookx.dtd">

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>FreeVikings Developer's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jakub</firstname> 
      <surname>Pavlik</surname>
      <email>severus@post.cz</email>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: INTRODUCTION.
       Who is this book for, what is it's aim, ... 
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      In January 2005 I wrote the first version of freeVikings, and, very
      proud of my first game (it was funless, boring, often crashing),
      published it on the Internet. A lot has changed since January 2005.
      I'm not so proud of my first game. And, I think, it's never more funless.
    </para>
    <para>
      FreeVikings now have several fancy features you expect a good game 
      to have. It's usually stable, 
      good-looking<footnote><para>This is a joke.
      Actually, freeVikings are still awful. I'm not able to do anything
      with this.</para></footnote> and extendable.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the developers make their application scriptable, they don't usually
      do it for themselves but for the users. Or they say they are doing it
      for users (everybody knows that the software developers only do things 
      for fun). FreeVikings are scriptable. 
      It means...<footnote><para>
      Yes, you're right. Actually it means I was playing with Ruby.
      But forget it, will you?</para></footnote>
      It means I want to give you the possibility
      of extending freeVikings with your own levels. You can catch
      Erik, Baleog and Olaf into your own traps. It seems good, doesn't it?
    </para>
    <para>
      So if you like freeVikings, have just a small amount of time for playing
      around a bit, ... Go on reading and make the best freeVikings level
      ever seen.
    </para>
    <para>
      This development guide is being written in the time of creation of
      freeVikings v. 0.7. Some of the interfaces described below can be changed
      in the future. Please, inform me if you find out that the examples 
      from this guide don't work or some interfaces don't behave as it is 
      described here.
    </para>
    <para>
      Everything in this guide is explained in the environment of unix-like
      operating system such as Linux. I would like to apologize to all the
      poor non-unix-systems-users.
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FIRST MAP
       How to create your own map, how to make it running (tell freeVikings
       where to find it) 
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>First map</title>

    <para>
      This chapter will guide you through the first steps of the freeVikings
      level developer. You will start with clean hands and end with a ready
      to use map.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Requirements</title>
      <para>
	What do you need? At least you need a computer 
	with a running<footnote><para>At first I wrote "well running".
	Then I looked at the text I had just written. FreeVikings do never run
	well... And I retyped the sentence quickly.</para></footnote>
	freeVikings installation and some plain text editor.
	If I could recommend you some, I would tell you to choose 
	<application>GNU Emacs</application> (because I like this great beast),
	but any editor with XML syntax highlighting is good enough for our 
	purpose and you can, if you are some kind of fanatic, use
	<application>ed</application> od <application>NotePad</application>
	of course.
      </para>
      <para>
	Another good thing to install on your computer is 
	<application>Tiled</application> 
	(<ulink url="http://mapeditor.org"/>), 
	a Java-written tile map editor.
	In fact you don't have to use it, it is also possible to make
	maps using the plain text editor, but I won't describe it here,
	because this kind of hand-made maps is ancient and deprecated.
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled.png"/>
      <para>
	<application>Tiled</application> produces simple but full-featured
	human-readable map<footnote><para>Well, not always human 
	readable...</para></footnote> 
	files in XML format.
      </para>
      <para>
	Just one more application. Some graphic editor for creating all kinds
	of graphics. I personally use <application>GIMP</application> 
	(<ulink url="http://www.gimp.org"/>).
	It has a lot of interesting features, is scriptable and free. 
	You will need some graphic editor to make your own tilesets
	(those distributed with freeVikings aren't still any good) and maybe
	your own creatures to make the new levels more interesting.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up Tiled</title>
      <para>
	First run Tiled. Go to the directory, where you have unpacked and
	installed it. On my machine it's 
	<filename>~/dist/tiled-0.5.0/dist/</filename>. 
	So I type on the terminal:
	<screen>
	  <computeroutput>[igneus@vidhost ~]$</computeroutput> <userinput>cd ~/dist/tiled-0.5.0/dist/</userinput>
	  <computeroutput>[igneus@vidhost dist]$</computeroutput> <userinput>java -jar tiled.jar</userinput>
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	The second command runs the Java application from archive 
	<filename>tiled.jar</filename>
	(in your installation it can have a different name!).
	After a moment you should see something like this:
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled_start.png" />
      <para>
	Of course some problems can (and probably will) occur. I, for example,
	had to delete the pre-compiled binaries (which are by default packed 
	in the distribution) and recompile the application, because it had been
	linked with newer libraries than I had on my machine.
      </para>
      <para>
	When <application>Tiled</application> is running, open the menu
	Edit and select item named Preferences. It has three tabs,
	only the one called Saving is important for us. Set it to the state 
	you can see on the image below, then click on Apply and OK.
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled_preferences.png"/>
      <para>
	This setup is the only one which works well with freeVikings.
	The other ones won't probably work well.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New map</title>
      <para>
	Now we will try to design a new map using
	<application>Tiled</application>. First you must have some tiles.
	Soon you will use your own fancy tiles or the awful ones which come
	packed with freeVikings, but now we will use the tiles I have prepared
	for this tutorial. Make a new directory somewhere. Then copy the image
	file with tiles to that directory. They are in the directory 
	with examples for this chapter:
	<filename>freeVikings/docs/develop_guide/examples/CH1_FirstMap/simple_tiles.png</filename>
      </para>
      <para>
	Go to <application>Tiled</application> and create a new map 
	(menu File, item New, or 
	<keycombo><keysym>Ctrl</keysym><keysym>N</keysym></keycombo>).
	A dialog will pop up, change the default values to those you can 
	see on the image below. Currently freeVikings can only work with tiles
	of size 40x40 pixels (maybe one day I'll make it more flexible) and 
	maps should have at least 16x12 tiles, because a smaller map doesn't
	fill the game window (and it's so small, that there will be no fun 
	for the vikings I think).
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_newmap.png"/>
      </para>
      <para>
	It's the time to load the tiles. From menu Tileset choose item 
	New tileset. If you want you can change the Tileset name, but it is 
	of no importance. What is important is to tick the checkbox
	labelled "Reference tileset image" and then click on the Browse button
	and find the image with tiles.
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_newtileset.png"/>
      </para>
      <para>
	In the bottom-left corner of <application>Tiled</application> window
	there is a really inconspicuous button (see the screenshot below).
	Press it.
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled_tilebutton.png"/>
      <para>
	The window which pops up is a "palette" of loaded tiles. 
	If you have done everything how I told you to, it should look like 
	this:
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_tilespalette.png"/>
	Click on one of the tiles, it automatically occurs on the button
	which causes the palette to pop up.
      </para>
      <para>
	Everything is ready, we can make our first map. Choose one of the two 
	tiles (they are awful, I know, I have never had a sense of art),
	<emphasis>choose the pencil tool</emphasis> from the toolbar on the 
	left and start to design
	the map.
      </para>
      <para>
	It could be useful for you to know that 
	<application>Tiled</application> gives you a possibility of zooming
	(zoom buttons are also in the toolbar). You should always try 
	the menu View, where you can switch on/off highlighting of cursor
	(not very useful), displaying the grid and coordinate numbers 
	(sometimes useful).
      </para>
      <para>
	So I have designed the map and saved it in the directory where I have
	the tileset image.
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_firstmap1.png"/>
	My (very simple) idea is that 
	the vikings will start in the top left corner and they'll always go
	down, in every story some tough monster will be waiting to eat them.
	After they bash the last monster, they will get into the lift
	which will take them to the EXIT in the top right corner of the map.
	Now we have the map, in the future chapters we'll add monsters etc.
      </para>
      <para>
	What I should have, but haven't told you:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>vikings are of size 80x100 px</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>so every corridor must be at least three 
	  tiles high</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>and every shaft at least three tiles 
	  wide</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	or the vikings won't be able to pass through...
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Metadata</title>
      <para>
	The map is nearly ready to use. We have to add just some additional
	information for the freeVikings game engine. First we add information
	about the solid layer.
      </para>
      <para>
	<application>Tiled</application> gives you a possibility to have 
	a multi-layer map and freeVikings support them. Usually you have
	one layer, which is called "solid layer". It's the layer of solid tiles
	which the vikings can't go through. Then you can have one or more
	layers, which are there just to make the map nicer. But of course 
	the game engine doesn't know which layer you want to be the solid one.
      </para>
      <para>
	From menu Map choose the item Properties. A small window will pop up,
	where you can edit a list of key-value pairs.
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_mapproperties.png"/>
	Add a new pair with key "solid_layer" and value, which is the name of 
	the layer you want to be solid (names of layers are in the layers panel
	on the right side of the <application>Tiled</application> window).
      </para>
      <tip>
	<title>One more property</title>
	<para>
	  <application>Tiled</application> sometimes "forgets" the last 
	  property from the list, so it can be useful to add one more
	  property (e.g. key "axb7", value "7785") which would be forgotten
	  if <application>Tiled</application> had a bad day.
	  (I haven't still found out when and why this error in 
	  <application>Tiled</application> occurs.
	</para>
      </tip>
      <para>
	Now you can save the map, it is ready to use.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Location data</title>
      <para>
	Before being able to run freeVikings with our new map, we must
	create a text file which describes it. From historic reasons
	this file is called "location file" and it's name is always
	<filename>location.xml</filename>.
	It's a XML file with special
	tags, so I recommend you to use some XML-friendly editor 
	(I usually use <application>Emacs</application>, less often
	<application>Scintilla</application> or 
	<application>FreeRide</application>; both of them come with Ruby
	One-Click-Installer).
	I assume you know at least the basics of XML (or HTML),
	but even if you don't it shouldn't be a problem for you to get the
	idea quickly and make the description files like an old XML guru.
      </para>
      <para>
	The file has a following structure (If you don't know much about XML, 
	you can copy it and use it as a skeleton of similar files 
	in future):
      </para>
      <programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" ?&gt;

&lt;location&gt;
  &lt;info&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;DevGuide: CH1: First map: example 1&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;author&gt;Jakub Pavlik&lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;/info&gt;

  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;password&gt;FRMP&lt;/password&gt;
    &lt;map src="<emphasis>firstmap_loc.tmx</emphasis>"/&gt;
    &lt;start horiz="<emphasis>50</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>60</emphasis>"/&gt;
    &lt;exit horiz="<emphasis>1110</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>70</emphasis>"/&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/location&gt;
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	The map description is divided into two blocks, info and body
	(inspired by HTML...). While the info block could be left out
	if you didn't want the map to have a name and to be signed 
	as a product of yours, the second block, body, is the essential one.
	FreeVikings wouldn't be able to load the map without it. All tags
	in the body section are compulsory.
      </para>
      <section>
	<title>Password</title>
	<programlisting>
	  &lt;password&gt;FRMP&lt;/password&gt;
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  Block tag password must contain a "word" made of four alphanumeric
	  characters (e.g. FRMP, ZF23, ...). A small, maybe important, note:
	  FreeVikings don't recognize upcase and downcase letters.
	  It defines password of the level. 
	</para>
	<para>
	  You should try to grep
	  through all levels packed in the freeVikings distribution to be sure
	  that you won't use a password which is already in use. Having grep
	  on your computer, it is quick, simple and useful:
	</para>
	<screen>
	  <prompt>[igneus@vidhost freeVikings]$</prompt> <userinput> grep FRMP ./locs/DefaultCampaign/*/*/location.xml</userinput>
	</screen>
      </section>
      <section>
	<title>Map</title>
	<programlisting>
	  &lt;map src="<emphasis>firstmap_loc.tmx</emphasis>"/&gt;	  
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  This tag says where to search for the map data. Name of the map file
	  is value of attribute src (I hope that all HTML-web-people are 
	  at home).
	</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	<title>Start and Exit</title>
	<programlisting>
    &lt;start horiz="<emphasis>50</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>60</emphasis>"/&gt;
    &lt;exit horiz="<emphasis>1110</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>70</emphasis>"/&gt;	  
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  Both tags have the same structure. Values of attributes horiz and 
	  vertic<footnote><para>horiz means x and vertic y;
	  in the past I wasn't able to remember which axis is x and 
	  which is y...</para></footnote> 
	  define two very important places on the map.
	</para>
	<graphic fileref="images/viking_position.png"/>
	<para>
	  Start is the initial position of top-left corners of the vikings.
	  How to get it? Remember that tiles are 40x40 px, vikings 80x100 px.
	  I hope it isn't hard to understand the idea of the image above.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Exit works in a similar way, but it isn't position of vikings, but 
	  position of the EXIT point that all of them have to reach to
	  pass to the next level.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Try it!</title>
      <para>
	We are now prepared to 
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter> 

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FREEVIKINGS BASICS
       Basic concepts of the game world.
       What is the Location, StaticObjects, ActiveObjects, Sprites, Items,
       what are they good for.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: SCRIPTING
       Writing location scripts with all the fancy stuff.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: COOL STUFF
       About themes, passwords, level suites.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: HOW TO CONTRIBUTE
       How to give your masterpiece to the free world.
       ==================================================================== -->
</book>
