<?xml version="1.0" ?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "docbookx.dtd">

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>FreeVikings Developer's Guide</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jakub</firstname> 
      <surname>Pavlik</surname>
      <email>severus@post.cz</email>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: INTRODUCTION.
       Who is this book for, what is it's aim, ... 
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      In January 2005 I wrote the first version of freeVikings, and, very
      proud of my first game (it was funless, boring, often crashing),
      published it on the Internet. A lot has changed since January 2005.
      I'm not so proud of my first game. And, I think, it's never more funless.
    </para>
    <para>
      FreeVikings now have several fancy features you expect a good game 
      to have. It's usually stable, 
      good-looking<footnote><para>This is a joke.
      Actually, freeVikings are still awful. I'm not able to do anything
      with this.</para></footnote> and extendable.
    </para>
    <para>
      When the developers make their application scriptable, they don't usually
      do it for themselves but for the users. Or they say they are doing it
      for users (everybody knows that the software developers only do things 
      for fun). FreeVikings are scriptable. It means...
      Yes, you're right. Actually it means I was playing with Ruby.
      But forget it, will you? It means I want to give you the possibility
      of extending freeVikings with your own levels. You can catch
      Erik, Baleog and Olaf into your own traps. It seems good, doesn't it?
    </para>
    <para>
      So if you like freeVikings, have just a small amount of time for playing
      around a bit, ... Go on reading and make the best freeVikings level
      ever seen.
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FIRST MAP
       How to create your own map, how to make it running (tell freeVikings
       where to find it) 
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>First map</title>

    <para>
      This chapter will guide you through the first steps of the freeVikings
      level developer. You will start with clean hands and end with a ready
      to use map.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Requirements</title>
      <para>
	What will you need? Well, it's onto you. Actually you don't need nearly
	anything. Just a well-running freeVikings installation and a plain
	text editor. But I would recommend you some better stuff. You should
	try to use a bit more sophisticated text editor such as Emacs,
	vim or SciTE. Why? Because of the syntax highlighting and checking.
	It's very helpful. Scripting mainly consists of XML and Ruby source
	editing. (Don't be afraid, it's simple.)
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Writing XML</title>
      <para>
	Let's start writing. Make yourself a directory you will store your
	freeVikings map in. Open a file with suffic .xml, e.g. 
	<filename>proto.xml</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
	Every XML file must start with a XML declaration.
      </para>
      <programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" ?&gt;
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	Then the document type definition usually goes, but freeVikings
	maps have no DTD yet, so we'll omit it.
      </para>
      <para>
	I hope you know HTML. XML looks very similar. Just tags...
	FreeVikings map is a XML file with special tags.
      </para>
      
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FREEVIKINGS BASICS
       Basic concepts of the game world.
       What is the Location, StaticObjects, ActiveObjects, Sprites, Items,
       what are they good for.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: SCRIPTING
       Writing location scripts with all the fancy stuff.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: COOL STUFF
       About themes, passwords, level suites.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: HOW TO CONTRIBUTE
       How to give your masterpiece to the free world.
       ==================================================================== -->
</book>
