<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<part>
  <title>Level-creator's tutorial</title>
  <subtitle>Learn to build your own freeVikings level</subtitle>

  <partintro>
    <para>
      In this part we will go chapter-by-chapter through the process of level
      creation. You will learn to make a valid freeVikings map, tell
      the game where to find it and finally to add some evil monsters.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the final stage (scripting monsters, items etc.) I expect you to
      have basic knowledge of Ruby programming language.
      If you don't know much about it but have some time to learn,
      choose one of many valuable introductory texts listed at
      <ulink url="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/documentation/">http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/documentation/</ulink>.
    </para>
  </partintro>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FIRST MAP
       How to create your own map, how to make it running (tell freeVikings
       where to find it) 
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>First map</title>

    <para>
      This chapter will guide you through the first steps of the freeVikings
      level developer. You will start with clean hands and end with a ready
      to use map.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Requirements</title>
      <para>
	What do you need? At least you need a computer 
	with a running<footnote><para>At first I wrote "well running".
	Then I looked at the text I had just written. FreeVikings do never run
	well... And I retyped the sentence quickly.</para></footnote>
	freeVikings installation and some plain text editor.
	If I could recommend you some, I would tell you to choose 
	<application>GNU Emacs</application> (because I like this great beast),
	but any editor with XML syntax highlighting is good enough for our 
	purpose and you can, if you are some kind of fanatic, use
	<application>ed</application> od <application>NotePad</application>
	of course.
      </para>
      <para>
	Another good thing to install on your computer is 
	<application>Tiled</application> 
	(<ulink url="http://mapeditor.org"/>), 
	a Java-written tile map editor.
	Version described in this tutorial is Tiled 0.5.0, but (with a possible
	delay) support for future versions will be added to freeVikings,
	because Tiled is a good tool and up to now new releases have always
	been worth upgrading.
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled.png"/>
      <para>
	Just one more application. Some graphic editor for creating all kinds
	of graphics. I personally use <application>GIMP</application> 
	(<ulink url="http://www.gimp.org"/>).
	It has a lot of interesting features, is scriptable and free. 
	You will need some graphic editor to make your own tilesets
	(those distributed with freeVikings aren't still any good) and maybe
	your own creatures to make the new levels more interesting.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Setting up Tiled</title>
      <para>
	First run Tiled. Go to the directory, where you have unpacked and
	installed it. On my machine it's 
	<filename>~/dist/tiled-0.5.0/dist/</filename>. 
	So I type on the terminal:
	<screen>
	  <computeroutput>[igneus@vidhost ~]$</computeroutput> <userinput>cd ~/dist/tiled-0.5.0/dist/</userinput>
	  <computeroutput>[igneus@vidhost dist]$</computeroutput> <userinput>java -jar tiled.jar</userinput>
	</screen>
      </para>
      <para>
	The second command runs the Java application from archive 
	<filename>tiled.jar</filename>
	(in your installation it can have a different name!).
	After a moment you should see something like this:
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled_start.png" />
      <para>
	Of course some problems can (and probably will) occur. I, for example,
	had to delete the pre-compiled binaries (which are by default packed 
	in the distribution) and recompile the application, because it had been
	linked with newer libraries than I had on my machine.
      </para>
      <para>
	When <application>Tiled</application> is running, open the menu
	Edit and select item named Preferences. It has three tabs,
	only the one called Saving is important for us. Set it to the state 
	you can see on the image below, then click on Apply and OK.
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled_preferences.png"/>
      <para>
	This setup is the only one which works well with freeVikings.
	The other ones won't probably work well.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New map</title>
      <para>
	Before starting a new map in Tiled, create a directory for it.
	Every freeVikings level has to be stored in it's own directory.
      </para>
      <para>
	Now we can design the map. First you must have some tiles.
	I have prepared a very simple set of two tiles for you -
	you will find the image in the directory of examples for this chapter:
	<filename>develop_guide/examples/CH1_FirstMap/simple_tiles.png</filename>.
	Copy it to the directory you prepared for your new map.
      </para>
      <para>
	Go to <application>Tiled</application> and create a new map 
	(<menuchoice>
	<guimenu>File</guimenu> <guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem>
	<shortcut>
	  <keycombo><keysym>Ctrl</keysym><keysym>N</keysym></keycombo>
	</shortcut>
	</menuchoice>).
	A dialog will pop up. Change the default values to those you can 
	see on the image below. Tile size 40x40 px is the most common one
	for freeVikings map (most of freeVikings standard tilesets are
	made in this tile size and so is also the tileset I prepared
	for this tutorial).
	Maps should have at least 16x12 tiles, because a smaller map doesn't
	fill the game window (and it's so small, that there will be no fun 
	for the vikings I think).
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_newmap.png"/>
      </para>
      <para>
	Load the tiles. From menu Tileset choose item 
	New tileset. If you want you can change the Tileset name, but it is 
	of no importance. What is important is to tick the checkbox
	labelled "Reference tileset image" and then click on the Browse button
	and find the image with tiles.
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_newtileset.png"/>
      </para>
      <para>
	In the bottom-left corner of <application>Tiled</application> window
	there is a really inconspicuous button (see the screenshot below).
	Press it.
      </para>
      <graphic fileref="images/tiled_tilebutton.png"/>
      <para>
	The window which pops up is a "palette" of loaded tiles. 
	If you have done everything how I told you to, it should look like 
	this:
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_tilespalette.png"/>
	Click on one of the tiles, it automatically occurs on the button
	which causes the palette to pop up.
      </para>
      <para>
	Everything is ready, we can make our first map. Choose one of the two 
	tiles (they are awful, I know, I have never had a sense of art),
	<emphasis>choose the pencil tool</emphasis> from the toolbar on the 
	left and start to design
	the map.
      </para>
      <para>
	It could be useful for you to know that 
	<application>Tiled</application> gives you a possibility of zooming
	(zoom buttons are also in the toolbar). You should always try 
	the menu View, where you can switch on/off highlighting of cursor
	(not very useful), displaying the grid and coordinate numbers 
	(sometimes useful).
      </para>
      <para>
	<graphic fileref="images/tiled_firstmap1.png"/>
	On the screenshot you can see example map which you can find
	in directory of examples for this chapter 
	(<filename>develop_guide/examples/CH1_FirstMap/</filename>).
	It is small (16x12 tiles - i.e. 640 x 480 px, because tile is
	40 x 40 px) and has a really stupid idea: vikings start at the
	top left corner and go down the stairs until they reach exit,
	which will be placed somewhere at the bottom right corner.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Location data</title>
      <para>
	Before being able to run freeVikings with our new map, we must
	create a text file which describes it. 
	This file is called "location file" and it's name is always
	<filename>location.xml</filename>.
	It's a XML file with special
	tags.
	I assume you know at least the basics of XML (or HTML),
	but even if you don't it shouldn't be a problem for you to get the
	idea quickly and make the description files like an old XML guru.
      </para>
      <para>
	The file has a following structure (If you don't know much about XML, 
	you can copy it and use it as a skeleton of similar files 
	in future):
      </para>
      <programlisting>
&lt;?xml version="1.0" ?&gt;

&lt;location&gt;
  &lt;info&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;DevGuide: CH1: First map: example 1&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;author&gt;Jakub Pavlik&lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;/info&gt;

  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;password&gt;FRMP&lt;/password&gt;
    &lt;map src="<emphasis>firstmap_loc.tmx</emphasis>"/&gt;
    &lt;start horiz="<emphasis>70</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>60</emphasis>"/&gt;
    &lt;exit horiz="<emphasis>520</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>320</emphasis>"/&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/location&gt;
      </programlisting>
      <para>
	The map description is divided into two blocks, info and body
	(inspired by HTML...). While the info block could be left out
	if you didn't want the map to have a name and to be signed 
	as a product of yours, the second block, body, is the essential one.
	FreeVikings wouldn't be able to load the map without it. All tags
	in the body section are compulsory.
      </para>
      <section>
	<title>Password</title>
	<programlisting>
	  &lt;password&gt;FRMP&lt;/password&gt;
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  Block tag password must contain a "word" made of four alphanumeric
	  characters (e.g. FRMP, ZF23, ...). A small, maybe important, note:
	  FreeVikings don't recognize upcase and downcase letters.
	  It defines password of the level. 
	</para>
	<para>
	  You should try to grep
	  through all levels packed in the freeVikings distribution to be sure
	  that you won't use a password which is already in use. Having grep
	  on your computer, it is quick, simple and useful:
	</para>
	<screen>
	  <prompt>[igneus@vidhost freeVikings]$</prompt> <userinput> grep FRMP ./locs/DefaultCampaign/*/*/location.xml</userinput>
	</screen>
      </section>
      <section>
	<title>Map</title>
	<programlisting>
	  &lt;map src="<emphasis>firstmap_loc.tmx</emphasis>"/&gt;	  
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  This tag says where to search for the map data. Name of the map file
	  is value of attribute src (I hope that all HTML-web-people are 
	  at home).
	</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	<title>Start and Exit</title>
	<programlisting>
    &lt;start horiz="<emphasis>70</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>60</emphasis>"/&gt;
    &lt;exit horiz="<emphasis>520</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>320</emphasis>"/&gt;	  
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  Both tags have the same structure. Values of attributes horiz and 
	  vertic<footnote><para>horiz means x and vertic y;
	  in the past I wasn't able to remember which axis is x and 
	  which is y...</para></footnote> 
	  define two very important places on the map.
	</para>
	<graphic fileref="images/viking_position.png"/>
	<para>
	  Start is the initial position of top-left corners of the vikings.
	  How to get it? Remember that tiles are 40x40 px, vikings 80x100 px.
	  I hope it isn't hard to understand the idea of the image above.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Exit works in a similar way, but it isn't position of vikings, but 
	  position of the EXIT point that all of them have to reach to
	  pass to the next level.
	</para>
	<para>
	  How to get the right position of start and exit?
	  Ask Tiled to show grid and coordinates:
	  <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>View</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Show Grid</guimenuitem>
	    <shortcut>
	      <keysym>Ctrl</keysym><keysym>G</keysym>
	    </shortcut>
	  </menuchoice>
	  and then
	  <menuchoice>
	    <guimenu>View</guimenu>
	    <guimenuitem>Show Coordinates</guimenuitem>
	  </menuchoice>
	  <graphic fileref="images/tiled_firstmap_start.png" />
	  I decided to start in the top left corner. Viking is 80px wide
	  and 100px high.
	  Surface of the first step is 5th row of tiles (y = 4*40 = 160px).
	  Vikings' y-coordinate has to be "floor - viking_height", i.e.
	  160 - 100 = 60. x-coordinatecan be anything higher than 40
	  (because first column of tiles is a wall)
	</para>
	<programlisting>
	  &lt;start horiz="<emphasis>70</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>60</emphasis>"/&gt;
	</programlisting>
	<para>
	  Note that you don't have to place vikings directly on the floor
	  as I've just done. You can as well place them somewhere in the free
	  space so that they fall at the beginning of level.
	</para>
	<para>
	  <graphic fileref="images/tiled_firstmap_exit.png" />
	  Position of exit is computed in a similar way. Exit's size is
	  40x40px (same as size of tile).
	</para>
	<programlisting>
	  &lt;exit horiz="<emphasis>520</emphasis>" vertic="<emphasis>320</emphasis>"/&gt;	  
	</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Try it!</title>
      <para>
	Our new map is now ready to the first test! Go to the freeVikings 
	directory and invoke freevikings.rb as follows:
	<screen>
	  <prompt>[igneus@vidhost freeVikings]$</prompt> <userinput>./freevikings.rb -l YOUR/LEVEL/DIRECTORY</userinput>
	</screen>
	For example I want to play the example level for this chapter:
	<screen>
	  <prompt>[igneus@vidhost freeVikings]$</prompt> <userinput>./freevikings.rb -l ./docs/develop_guide/examples/CH1_FirstMap/</userinput>
	</screen>
	Option <option>-l</option> tells freeVikings to load level
	(or, as you will see later, a set of levels) from directory
	given as argument to the option. So when you start new game
	as usual, instead of the familiar first ice level with bear
	you see your new level!
	<graphic fileref="images/firstmap_test.png" />
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: TILESETS
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Tilesets</title>

    <para>
      In the previous chapter we created a simple map built of two tiles.
      Any game developer must have laughed a lot - two tiles are a really
      poor tileset. You can look at tilesets shipped with freeVikings -
      you can find them in directory <filename>gfx/tilesets/</filename>.
      Since all of them are really poor, you'll probably want to make your
      own.
    </para>
    <note>
      <title>Where are tilesets for most freeVikings standard levels?</title>
      <para>
	Most of levels from the default campaign (ice levels etc.) are
	legacy from "pre-Tiled" epoch. They are built of tiles stored
	file-per-tile; you can find them in subdirectories of
	<filename>gfx/themes/</filename> (together with images
	of some theme-specific objects).
      </para>
    </note>
    <para>
      Tileset is simply a PNG image where tiles are painted next to each other
      without any gaps. All tiles of a tileset must be of the same size.
      Recommended tile size is 40x40px. However, freeVikings releases after 0.6
      support even custom-sized tilesets. The only limitation is that
      all tilesets used in one map have the same size (even if Tiled
      provides limited possibility to combine different tile sizes in one map!)
    </para>
    <para>
      It is really important that your tileset image is in PNG format, because
      Tiled can't work with other graphic formats (freeVikings can).
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: SCRIPTING
       Writing location scripts.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Scripting</title>

    <para>
      For reading of this chapter it is strongly recommended that you've
      spent a few hours programming in Ruby, because otherwise you will have
      big problems - it isn't hard to understand and copy basic syntactic
      constructs, but as soon as errors occur, you can't go on without
      some Ruby programming experience.
    </para>
    <para>
      Look at the directory with examples for this chapter 
      (<filename>examples/CH3_Scripting/</filename>). I have prepared
      two levels for you. In directory <filename>FullLevel</filename>
      you will find level with several objects - you can try it right now
      to see how it works and look into it as to kind of reference.
      Directory <filename>EmptyLevel</filename> contains the same map
      as FullLevel, but without any objects. You should copy
      EmptyLevel somewhere and follow this tutorial. If you
      follow it carefully step-by-step, you will finally get
      the same as is in FullLevel.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Tell freeVikings about a script file</title>
      <para>
	huh
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: ADVANCED MAP TOPICS
       more layers; solid layer; foreground and background layers
       ==================================================================== -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Advanced mapping topics</title>

    <para>
      To know full magic of freeVikings map creation, you should be able
      to add some background to your map and possibly also some
      foreground so that os some places vikings can e.g. walk behind
      a semi-transparent wall.
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: GAME OBJECTS
       What is the Location, StaticObjects, ActiveObjects, Sprites, Items,
       what are they good for.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: FROM SEPARATE LEVEL TO COMPLEX WORLD
       About themes, passwords, level suites.
       ==================================================================== -->

  <!-- ====================================================================
       Chapter: HOW TO CONTRIBUTE
       How to give your masterpiece to the free world.
       ==================================================================== -->

</part>
