<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>freeVikings: User's Manual</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Jakub</firstname> 
      <surname>Pavlik</surname>
      <email>severus@post.cz</email>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <!-- chapter: INSTALLATION -->

  <chapter id="chap_install">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>
      Game is written completely in Ruby. While Ruby is an interpreted 
      programming language, it isn't needed (and most probably even not 
      possible) to compile the code. You just have to install Ruby
      interpreter and a few libraries. Both the interpreter and all needed
      libraries are licensed by open source licenses and you can download
      them all for free.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Ruby - get it and install</title>
      <section>
	<title>Linux</title>
	<para>
	  Ruby is included in most Linux distributions, so the easiest way
	  for you might be to install it using the package manager.
	  Source archive (if you prefer to compile from source - e.g. your
	  distribution doesn't contain up-to-date ruby package and you don't
	  want to upgrade to a newer distribution) can be downloaded at 
	  <ulink url="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/"/>.
	</para>
      </section>
      <section>
	<title>Windows</title>
	<para>
	  Go to <ulink url="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/"/> and
	  download some of the packages marked as stable. I personally
	  have a good experience with the "One Click Installer" - it is
	  a regular self-extracting EXE installer which includes 
	  the interpreter, documentation, interactive shell, ri documentation
	  browser, many useful libraries and Nice Ruby IDE.
	</para>
	<para>
	  If you are installing Ruby from the One Click Installer,
	  you might want <emphasis>not to check</emphasis> option 
	  "Enable RubyGems" (see image below).
	  <graphic fileref="images/oneclickrubygems.png"/>
	  If you check this option, the installer appends option '-rubygems' 
	  to environment variable <envar>RUBYOPT</envar> which causes
	  Ruby to always load RubyGems.
	  FreeVikings before release 0.6 (and many more applications
	  built upon the RUDL library) wouldn't work then.
	  On the other side, you may want to <emphasis>check</emphasis>
	  this option, because some useful libraries (such as Log4r, which
	  is useful when you want to see detailed freeVikings debugging
	  data) are included in the installer as gems. But even if you
	  don't check this option, you can still use RubyGems when you need -
	  just start ruby from the commandline with option '-rubygems':
	  <screen>
	    <prompt>&gt;</prompt> <userinput>ruby -rubygems freevikings.rb</userinput>
	  </screen>
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Libraries</title>
      <para>
	Libraries you have to install:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>RUDL 
	  (get from SourceForge)</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	Those which should be included in Ruby distributions and you need 
	to install them if they aren't:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>REXML 
	  (usually packed with Ruby)</para></listitem>
	  <listitem><para>YAML</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	Optional:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>Log4r 
	  (included in Ruby One-Click installer as a gem; 
	  optional since fV 0.6, get from RAA)</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	Redistributed with freeVikings:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem><para>script 
	  (included since fV 0.6; get from RAA 
	  in order to play older versions)</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>

      <section>
	<title>RUDL</title>
	<para>
	  RUDL is SDL port for Ruby. 
	</para>
	<section>
	  <title>Linux</title>
	  <para>
	    First check you have all libraries listed below. RUDL can build
	    even missing some of them, but it may cause situation that
	    freeVikings won't work. The good message is, that most Linux
	    distributions include binary packages of these libraries.
	  </para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>SDL</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>SDL_gfx</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>SDL_image</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>SDL_mixer</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>SDL_ttf</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>SDL_net</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>smpeg</para></listitem>
	    <listitem><para>freetype</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	  <para>
	    Some Linux distributions may include RUDL
	    as a binary package, but I don't know any. So most of us have to
	    download from SourceForge: <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=42958&amp;package_id=35163"/>. Download latest
	    source package (at the time of writing of this document it was
	    release 0.8).
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Unpack downloaded RUDL archive and ener the new directory rudl-0.8
	    <screen>
	      <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>ruby extconf.rb</userinput>
	    </screen>
	    This checks for required libraries and creates Makefiles.
	    <screen>
	      <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>make</userinput>
	    </screen>
	    As superuser type
	    <screen>
	      <prompt>#</prompt> <userinput>make install</userinput>
	    </screen>
	    (If you needed to know how to compile and use RUDL not having
	    access to superuser account, mail me and I will extend this
	    manual for this case.)
	  </para>
	</section>
	<section>
	  <title>Windows</title>
	  <para>
	    Get latest windows binary package from <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=42958&amp;package_id=35163"/>.
	    Usually two Windows binary archives are provided - get the one
	    named 
	    rudl-0.x-for-ruby-1.x.x-<emphasis>setup-releasebuild</emphasis>.zip
	    Unpack it. Execute script install-on-windows.rb .
	    It will open shell window and ask you two questions:
	    if it should continue installing RUDL (you want to answer 'y')
	    and where you want additional DLLs to be put (if you don't know
	    any better place for them, let the installer put them in your
	    ruby/bin directory - I have them there and it works well)
	  </para>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>REXML</title>
	
	<para>
	  REXML is a very powerful XML-processing library and (I think since
	  ruby-1.8.2) it is distributed together with Ruby as a part of it's
	  library. So if you installed Ruby e.g. from source or on Windows
	  from the One-Click installer, you already have REXML.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Some Linux distro-makers like to provide it 
	  as a separate packege so look for it.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Simple test to check if REXML is present in your system:
	  <screen>
	    <prompt>[igneus@vidhost tmp]$</prompt> <userinput>irb</userinput>
	    <prompt>irb(main):001:0></prompt> <userinput>require 'rexml/document'</userinput>
	    <computeroutput>=> true</computeroutput>
	  </screen>
	  Great!
	  <screen>
	    <prompt>irb(main):001:0></prompt> <userinput>require 'rexml/document'</userinput>
<computeroutput>LoadError: no such file to load -- rexml/document
        from (irb):1:in `require'
        from (irb):1</computeroutput>
	  </screen>
	  Here, unfortunatelly, you will have to try to find REXML.
	  You can found the archive 
	  at <ulink url="http://raa.ruby-lang.org/project/rexml/"/>.
	  Unpack it and follow instructions from the file INSTALL.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>YAML</title>
	<para>
	  I can't remember if YAML is distributed together with Ruby or not.
	  I hope it is (I have ruby-1.9.0 source for playing and it includes
	  YAML library), but if you get LoadError either on freeVikings
	  start or on level loading, saying, that you haven't YAML,
	  it's time to look for the library and send me an e-mail
	  (Hey, your manual is incomplete!).
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Log4r</title>
	<para>
	  Since freeVikings 0.6 you don't need this library to run freeVikings,
	  because it is useful mainly for development and freeVikings contain
	  a simple bypass which is used if Log4r isn't found. However,
	  even as a non-developer, you might want this library in order
	  to get better informed about what's happening inside freeVikings -
	  e.g. if the game regularly crashes at startup and you want to
	  send me a bug report.
	</para>
	<para>
	  Ruby One-Click installer contains Log4r as a gem. If you
	  want to play freeVikings with Log4r enabled, start game
	  from the commandline:
	  <screen>
	    <prompt>C:\kuba\freeVikings&gt;</prompt> <userinput>ruby -rubygems freevikings.rb</userinput>
	  </screen>
	</para>
	<para>
	  It is possible to install Log4r using gems:
	  <screen>
	    <prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>gem install log4r</userinput>
	  </screen>
	  (If you have problems using gems, don't ask me - I haven't solved 
	  them yet myself.)
	  Remember that you can't use this for freeVikings before release 0.6.
	</para>
	<para>
	  The second way is to download Log4r as an archive and install it
	  manually: 
	  get it from <ulink url="http://raa.ruby-lang.org/project/log4r/"/>
	  and follow instructions in file INSTALL.
	</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Script</title>
	<para>
	  This small but great library is distributed together with freeVikings
	  since release 0.6, but if you want to play older versions, you
	  can get it 
	  at <ulink url="http://raa.ruby-lang.org/project/script/"/>.
	</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!-- chapter: RUNNING -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Running freeVikings</title>
    <para>
      You have installed Ruby and all required libraries. Now you can try 
      to run freeVikings. For the first time it is useful to invoke
      game from the command line, because if it crashes, you see the error
      output.
    </para>
    <para>
      You may also want to give some arguments. Type
      <screen>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>ruby freevikings --help</userinput>
      </screen>
      for full listing of supported options.
    </para>
    <para>
      Example: disable sound (e.g. you hate freeVikings music or want to
      listen to your favourite mp3s while playing freeVikings).
      <screen>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>ruby freevikings --sound off</userinput>
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      Another example: Play other campaign than the Default one.
      <screen>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>ruby freevikings -l locs/RubyCampaign</userinput>
      </screen>
      Look at the directory locs. Currently it contains three
      campaign:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>DafaultCampaign - 6 levels of varying quality</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>RubyCampaign - one stupid, but hot-new level</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>TestsCampaign - 12 small stupid levels for testing of different features of the game (mainly monsters) and 2 ancient levels which I wasn't able to delete because of nostalgy</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <!-- chapter: CONTROLS -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Game controls</title>

    <para>
      I designed freeVikings with aim of immitating Lost Vikings where
      the old game was good and making it better where needed.
      Following this philosophy I am doing my best to copy keyboard controls
      inside game and add a few mouse controls (currently it is possible
      to use mouse for switching between vikings, selecting item inside 
      inventory and moving items between vikings). On the other side
      I implemented exitting and giving up differently, because
      it took several minutes before I guessed how to do this in Lost Vikings.
    </para>
    <para>
      General:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Kill game immediately: [X] button on the window</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Restart level: <keycap>F2</keycap></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Return to menu: <keycap>Esc</keycap></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Pause: <keycap>P</keycap></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Switching between vikings:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Switch to next viking: <keycap>Page Up</keycap></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Switch to previous viking: right <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> or <keycap>Page Down</keycap></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Select any viking: left-click on his portrait</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      All three vikings:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Move left/right: cursor key left/right</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Switch something on: <keycap>S</keycap> or cursor key up</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Switch something off: <keycap>F</keycap> or cursor key down</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Use item: <keycap>E</keycap> or <keycap>U</keycap></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Baleog (green guy):
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Use sword: <keycap>space</keycap></para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Shoot arrow: <keycap>D</keycap></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Erik (blue guy):
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Jump: <keycap>space</keycap></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      Olaf (yellow guy):
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Change shield position: <keycap>space</keycap></para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Maybe the most tricky thing in Lost Vikings was inventory using.
      In freeVikings this traditional tricky keyboard-commanded system has 
      been preserved,
      but additional possibility to use mouse instead has been added.
    </para>
    <para>
      Items are collected as vikings touch them, so you don't to bother
      with pushing any key to collect them. They are storted in vikings'
      inventories. Every inventory has four slots and if these are full,
      viking cannot collect any more items. To make some slots free,
      viking can either delete some item (which might be useful later!)
      or give it to any of his friends.
    </para>
    <para>
      On the image below you can see the bottom of game screen.
      Active viking is Erik (his portraid is coloured - the others are black 
      and white). The yellow frame shows which item in the inventory is active.
      <graphic fileref="images/inventory_normal.png"/>
      Press <keycap>Tab</keycap>. Game is paused and the yellow frame
      started blinking. You can use cursor keys to move yellow frame
      around the inventory. If you press <keycap>Delete</keycap> now,
      the active item is deleted. Press <keycap>Tab</keycap> again
      to unpause and continue playing.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can select another item in viking's inventory also by clicking on it.
      Unfortunatelly deleting items using a mouse hasn't been implemented yet.
    </para>
    <para>
      The most complicated case: you need to move one of Baleog's items 
      to Erik. Before it is possible, all the exchange participants
      (Erik and Baleog in this case) must touch each other.
      Now press <keycap>Tab</keycap> (pauses game, switches to 
      'inventory mode') and then <keycap>Space</keycap> (which switches
      to 'items exchanging mode'). Frame in active viking's inventory
      is now green - see image below -  and blinking. Inventories of
      vikings which can't participate in the exchange get darker
      (see Olaf's). Use cursor keys left/right to move active item between 
      vikings. Than push <keycap>Space</keycap> to switch to 'normal inventory 
      mode' again.
    </para>
    <graphic fileref="images/inventory_move.png"/>
    <para>
      You can do the same - move items between vikings - also using a mouse.
      But it has a slight disadvantage - while this operation has no
      real-time visual effect, you have to check yourself that the vikings
      touch etc. If the item doesn't disappear from one and appear in another
      inventory, try again, try to move vikings, ... (or learn to use
      the 'keyboard way' and wait for next release with better mouse support).
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <!-- CHAPTER: TROUBLESHOOTING -->

  <chapter>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>

    <para>
      While playing with freeVikings, you can encounter several kinds 
      of problems. It is usually useful to start program from console,
      because code of freeVikings is full of debugging output and logging
      engine is set up so that it should print all important messages
      to the standard error output. You should also consider running
      freeVikings with Log4r (as discussed in <xref linkend="chap_install"/>)
    </para>
    <para>
      If you encounter an error and you can't solve it yourself, you can
      ask me for support. Before writing an e-mail, you should
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem><para>try to repeat the error and write where and in
	which circumstances it occurs</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>copy content of console (you can send it either as
	text or as screenshot) - error messages printed there are really 
	valuable for me</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>pack content of directory freeVikings/log
	(e.g. as a ZIP archive or as a tarball)</para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      I'll do my best to help you.
    </para>
  </chapter>
</book>
